Everybody talks about happiness these days.
يتحدث الجميع هذه الأيام عن السعادة.
I had somebody count the number of books
لقد قمت بتكليف شخص ما لإحصاء الكتب
with "happiness" in the title published in the last five years
ذات العنوان " السعادة" التي نُشرت في الخمس سنوات الماضية
and they gave up after about 40, and there were many more.
وقد أعطاني حوالي 40، وهناك المزيد أكثر.
There is a huge wave of interest in happiness,
توجد موجة عارمة من الإهتمام بالسعادة،
among researchers.
بين الباحثين.
There is a lot of happiness coaching.
وهناك الكثير من التدريب على السعادة.
Everybody would like to make people happier.
سيرغب كل في جعل الناس أكثر سعادةً.
But in spite of all this flood of work,
لكن رغماً عن هذا الفيضان من العمل،
there are several cognitive traps
فهناك عدة فخاخ معرفية
that sort of make it almost impossible to think straight
التي تجعل من المستحيل تقريباً التفكير مباشرة
about happiness.
حول السعادة.
And my talk today will be mostly about these cognitive traps.
وحديثي اليوم سيكون في الغالب حول تلك الفخاخ المعرفية.
This applies to laypeople thinking about their own happiness,
هذا ينطبق على الأشخاص العاديين يفكرون بسعادتهم،
and it applies to scholars thinking about happiness,
وينطبق على العلماء المفكرين حول السعادة،
because it turns out we're just as messed up as anybody else is.
لأنه وضح أننا مرتبكون كأي شخص آخر.
The first of these traps
أول هذه الفخاخ
is a reluctance to admit complexity.
هو التردد حول الإعتراف بالتعقيد.
It turns out that the word "happiness"
وقد وضح أن كلمة السعادة
is just not a useful word anymore,
ليست كلمة مفيدة بعد الآن
because we apply it to too many different things.
لأننا نطبقها على الكثير من الأشياء المختلفة.
I think there is one particular meaning to which we might restrict it,
وأعتقد أن هناك معنى واحد محدد الذي ينبغي أن نلتزم به
but by and large,
لكن، إلى حد كبير،
this is something that we'll have to give up
هو شئ سيتوجب علينا تركه
and we'll have to adopt the more complicated view
وينبغي علينا تبني النظرة الأكثر تعقيداً
of what well-being is.
عن ماهية الرفاه.
The second trap is a confusion between experience and memory;
الفخ الثاني هو الإرتباك بين التجربة والذاكرة:
basically, it's between being happy in your life,
في الأساس فهي بين أن تكون سعيداً في حياتك
and being happy about your life
وأن تكون سعيداً حول حياتك
or happy with your life.
أو سعيداً مع حياتك.
And those are two very different concepts,
وهذان مفهومان مختلفان جداً،
and they're both lumped in the notion of happiness.
وكلاهما تم جمعهما في مفهوم السعادة.
And the third is the focusing illusion,
والثالث هو تركيز الوهم،
and it's the unfortunate fact that we can't think about any circumstance
وهي الحقيقة غير السارة بأننا لا نستطيع التفكير حول أي ظروف
that affects well-being
تقوم بالتأثير على الرفاه
without distorting its importance.
بدون التشويش على أهميته.
I mean, this is a real cognitive trap.
أعني، هذا فخ معرفي حقيقي.
There's just no way of getting it right.
وليس هناك طريقة لفهمه بصورة صحيحة.
Now, I'd like to start with an example
الآن، أرغب في البداية بمثال
of somebody who had a question-and-answer session
لشخص ما الذي حضر جلسة أسئلة وأجوبة
after one of my lectures reported a story,
بعد أن ذكرت في احدى محاضراتي قصة.
and that was a story --
[غير واضح...]
He said he'd been listening to a symphony,
لقد قال أنه كان يستمع إلى السيمفونية
and it was absolutely glorious music
وقد كانت موسيقى متألقة جداً
and at the very end of the recording,
وفي نهاية التسجيل،
there was a dreadful screeching sound.
كان هناك صوت صراخ مروع.
And then he added, really quite emotionally,
ثم أضاف، بصورة عاطفية جداً،
it ruined the whole experience.
لقد خرّبت التجربة برمتها.
But it hadn't.
لكنها لم تفعل.
What it had ruined were the memories of the experience.
ما تخرّب كان هو ذكريات التجربة.
He had had the experience.
لقد مرّ بتلك التجربة.
He had had 20 minutes of glorious music.
وقد أستمتع ب 20 دقيقة من الموسيقى المتألقة.
They counted for nothing
ولم تُحسب لأي شئ
because he was left with a memory;
لأنه خلّف الذاكرة.
the memory was ruined,
الذكرى قد خُرّبت،
and the memory was all that he had gotten to keep.
وكانت الذاكرة هي كل ما عليه الإحتفاظ به.
What this is telling us, really,
ما يخبرنا به هذا، حقاً،
is that we might be thinking of ourselves and of other people
هو أننا ربما نفكر بأنفسنا وبقية الناس
in terms of two selves.
بأننا وهم نملك نوعين من النفسيات
There is an experiencing self,
هناك نفسية التجربة،
who lives in the present
التي تعيش في الحاضر
and knows the present,
وتعرف الحاضر،
is capable of re-living the past,
وقادرة على إعادة العيش في الماضي،
but basically it has only the present.
لكن في الأساس لديها فقط الحاضر.
It's the experiencing self that the doctor approaches --
إنها نفسية التجربة التي يصلها الطبيب --
you know, when the doctor asks,
كما تعلمون، حينما يسأل الطبيب،
"Does it hurt now when I touch you here?"
" هل يؤلمك الآن عندما ألمسك هنا؟"
And then there is a remembering self,
ثم هناك نفسية الذكرى،
and the remembering self is the one that keeps score,
ونفسية الذكرى هي التي تبقي النتيجة،
and maintains the story of our life,
وتحافظ على قصة حياتنا،
and it's the one that the doctor approaches
وهي تلك التي يقترب منها الطبيب
in asking the question,
عند طرح السؤال،
"How have you been feeling lately?"
" كيف كنت تحس مؤخراً؟"
or "How was your trip to Albania?" or something like that.
أو " كيف كانت رحلتك إلى البانيا؟" أو شئ من هذا القبيل.
Those are two very different entities,
تلك هما شيئين مختلفين جدا ،
the experiencing self and the remembering self,
نفسية التجربة و نفسية الذاكرة
and getting confused between them is part of the mess
والخلط بينهما هو جزء من الكارثة
about the notion of happiness.
لمفهوم السعادة.
Now, the remembering self
الآن نفسية الذاكرة
is a storyteller.
تروي القصص.
And that really starts with a basic response of our memories --
وذلك بالفعل يبدأ مع الإستجابة الاساسية لذاكرتنا--
it starts immediately.
إنها تبدأ في الحال.
We don't only tell stories when we set out to tell stories.
نحن لا نقوم فقط بحكي القصص عندما نكون جاهزين لقص القصص.
Our memory tells us stories,
إن ذاكرتنا تخبرنا بالقصص،
that is, what we get to keep from our experiences
ذلك هو، ما نحتفظ به من تجاربنا
is a story.
هو القصة.
And let me begin with one example.
ودعوني أبدأ بمثال.
This is an old study.
هذه دراسة قديمة.
Those are actual patients undergoing a painful procedure.
هؤلاء هم مرضى حقيقيون يخضعون لإجراءات مؤلمة.
I won't go into detail. It's no longer painful these days,
لن أدلف إلى التفاصيل. لم تعد مؤلمة هذه الأيام،
but it was painful when this study was run in the 1990s.
لكنها كانت مؤلمة حينما انجزت خلال التسعينات.
They were asked to report on their pain every 60 seconds.
لقد طُلب منهم الإبلاغ عن ألمهم كل 60 ثانية.
Here are two patients,
وها هم مريضين.
those are their recordings.
وتلك هي التسجيلات.
And you are asked, "Who of them suffered more?"
ويطلب منك، " من منهم عانى من الألم أكثر؟"
And it's a very easy question.
وهو سؤال سهل للغاية.
Clearly, Patient B suffered more --
بكل وضوح، عانى المريض "ب" من الألم أكثر.
his colonoscopy was longer,
كان قولونه أطول،
and every minute of pain that Patient A had,
وكل دقيقة من الألم عانى منها المريض "أ"
Patient B had, and more.
كانت أكثر لدى المريض "ب".
But now there is another question:
لكن هناك سؤالاً آخراً:
"How much did these patients think they suffered?"
" كم يحس أؤلئك المرضى أنهم عانوا من الألم؟"
And here is a surprise.
وهنا المفاجأة:
The surprise is that Patient A
والمفاجأة هي أن المريض "أ"
had a much worse memory of the colonoscopy
لديه ذكريات أسوأ بكثير من القولون
than Patient B.
عن المريض "ب".
The stories of the colonoscopies were different,
هذه القصص عن القولونات كانت مختلفة
and because a very critical part of the story is how it ends.
ولأن جزءا هاما جدا من القصة هو كيف تنتهي --
And neither of these stories is very inspiring or great --
وليست أي من هاتين القصتين ملهمة جداً أو عظيمة--
but one of them is this distinct ... (Laughter)
لكن أحداهما هي هذه المتميزة...(ضحك)
but one of them is distinctly worse than the other.
لكن أحداهما متميزة بالسوء أكثر من الأخرى.
And the one that is worse
وتلك التي هي أسوأ
is the one where pain was at its peak at the very end;
كانت هي حيث كان الألم في ذروته في النهاية.
it's a bad story.
إنها قصة سيئة.
How do we know that?
كيف نعرف ذلك؟
Because we asked these people after their colonoscopy,
لأننا سألنا أؤلئك الناس بعد تجربة منظارهم،
and much later, too,
وبعدها بكثير، ايضاً.
"How bad was the whole thing, in total?"
" كم كان سيئاً كل شئ، في المجموع؟"
And it was much worse for A than for B, in memory.
وقد كان ذكريات أكثر سوءً بكثير عند "أ" منه عند "ب".
Now this is a direct conflict
الآن هذا هو تناقض مباشر
between the experiencing self and the remembering self.
بين نفسية التجربة ونفسية الذكرى.
From the point of view of the experiencing self,
من وجهة نظر نفسية التجربة،
clearly, B had a worse time.
بكل وضوح، "ب" عانى أوقاتاً أسوأ.
Now, what you could do with Patient A,
الآن، ماذا يمكننا أن نفعل مع المريض "أ"،
and we actually ran clinical experiments,
وقد قمنا في الواقع بتجارب سريرية،
and it has been done, and it does work --
وقد تم إنجازها، وهي ناجحة،
you could actually extend the colonoscopy of Patient A
يمكنك في الواقع توسيع قولون المريض "أ"
by just keeping the tube in without jiggling it too much.
بمجرد الإبقاء على الأنبوب بدون هزه كثيراً.
That will cause the patient
ذلك سيتسبب في معاناة
to suffer, but just a little
المريض، قليلاً فقط
and much less than before.
وأقل بكثير من السابق.
And if you do that for a couple of minutes,
وإذا فعلت ذلك لعدة دقائق،
you have made the experiencing self
فأنك قد جعلت نفسية التجربة
of Patient A worse off,
للمريض "أ" أسوأ حالاً،
and you have the remembering self of Patient A
ولديك نفسية الذكرى للمريض "أ"
a lot better off,
أفضل حالاً بكثير،
because now you have endowed Patient A
لأنك الآن تركت المريض "أ"
with a better story
مع قصة أفضل
about his experience.
حول تجربته.
What defines a story?
ما الذي يعرّف القصة؟
And that is true of the stories
وذلك ينطبق على القصص
that memory delivers for us,
التي ترسلها الذاكرة لنا،
and it's also true of the stories that we make up.
وهو كذلك صحيح على القصص التي نصنعنها.
What defines a story are changes,
الذي يعرّف القصة هي التغييرات،
significant moments and endings.
اللحظات المهمة والنهايات.
Endings are very, very important
النهايات مهمة جداً جداً
and, in this case, the ending dominated.
و في هذه الحالة، طغت النهاية.
Now, the experiencing self
الآن، ذاكرة التجربة
lives its life continuously.
تعيش حياتها بصورة مستمرة.
It has moments of experience, one after the other.
إنها لحظات التجربة، واحدة تلو الأخرى.
And you can ask: What happens to these moments?
وأنت تسأل: ماذا يحدث لهذه اللحظات؟
And the answer is really straightforward:
والجواب هو مباشر حقاً.
They are lost forever.
إنها تضيع إلى الأبد.
I mean, most of the moments of our life --
أعني، معظم اللحظات في حياتنا --
and I calculated, you know, the psychological present
ولقد حسبت -- كما تعلمون، يقال أن حاضر النفسية
is said to be about three seconds long;
يدوم لفترة ثلاث ثواني.
that means that, you know,
الذي يعني أنه، كما تعلمون،
in a life there are about 600 million of them;
خلال فترة الحياة، هناك 600 مليون منها.
in a month, there are about 600,000 --
في الشهر، هناك 600،000.
most of them don't leave a trace.
معظمها لا تخلف أثراً.
Most of them are completely ignored
معظمها يتم تجاهلها كلياً
by the remembering self.
بواسطة نفسية الذكرى.
And yet, somehow you get the sense
وحتى أنك تشعر بطريقة ما
that they should count,
أنه ينبغي أخذها في الحسبان،
that what happens during these moments of experience
لما يحدث خلال لحظات التجربة هذه
is our life.
لانها حياتنا.
It's the finite resource that we're spending
إنها الموارد المحدودة التي نستهلكها
while we're on this earth.
أثناء وجودنا على هذه الأرض.
And how to spend it
وكيفية قضائها،
would seem to be relevant,
سيبدو مترابطاً،
but that is not the story
لكن ليست تلك القصة
that the remembering self keeps for us.
التي تبقيها لنا نفسية الذكرى.
So we have the remembering self
إذاً فنحن لدينا نفسية الذكرى
and the experiencing self,
ونفسية التجربة،
and they're really quite distinct.
وهما حقاً مستقلتان.
The biggest difference between them
أكبر الفوارق بينهما
is in the handling of time.
يكمن في التعامل مع الزمن.
From the point of view of the experiencing self,
من وجهة نظر نفسية التجربة،
if you have a vacation,
إذا ذهبت في عطلة،
and the second week is just as good as the first,
وكان الأسبوع الثاني جيداً كما الأسبوع الأول،
then the two-week vacation
حينها فالأسبوع الثاني للعطلة
is twice as good as the one-week vacation.
سيكون افضل مرتين عن الأسبوع الأول.
That's not the way it works at all for the remembering self.
وليست تلك نفس الطريقة التي تعمل بها نفسية الذكرى.
For the remembering self, a two-week vacation
بالنسبة لنفسية الذكرى، فان عطلة الأسبوعين
is barely better than the one-week vacation
بالكاد أفضل من عطلة أسبوع واحد
because there are no new memories added.
لأنه لا توجد ذكريات جديدة لتضاف.
You have not changed the story.
ولم تقم أنت بتغيير القصة.
And in this way,
وبهذه الطريقة،
time is actually the critical variable
فان الوقت في الواقع متغير حرج
that distinguishes a remembering self
يقوم بالتفريق بين نفسية الذكرى
from an experiencing self;
من نفسية التجربة.
time has very little impact on the story.
للوقت تأثير قليل على هذه القصة.
Now, the remembering self does more
الآن، تقوم نفسية الذكرى بأكثر
than remember and tell stories.
من التذكر وإخبار القصص.
It is actually the one that makes decisions
إنها في الواقع التي تتخذ القرارات
because, if you have a patient who has had, say,
لأنه، إن كان لديك مريض مرّ، لنقل،
two colonoscopies with two different surgeons
بفحصين للقولون مع جراحين مختلفين
and is deciding which of them to choose,
ويقرر أي منها سيختار،
then the one that chooses
عندئذ فالفحص الذي يختاره
is the one that has the memory that is less bad,
هو الفحص الذي لديه ذكريات أقل سوءا،
and that's the surgeon that will be chosen.
وذلك الجراح الذي سيتم إختياره.
The experiencing self
نفسية التجربة
has no voice in this choice.
ليس لديها قرار في هذا الخيار.
We actually don't choose between experiences,
نحن في الواقع لا نقوم بالإختيار بين التجارب.
we choose between memories of experiences.
نحن نختار من بين ذكريات التجارب.
And even when we think about the future,
وحتى عندما نفكر بالمستقبل،
we don't think of our future normally as experiences.
فنحن لا نفكر بالمستقبل عادةً كتجارب.
We think of our future
نحن نفكر بمستقبلنا
as anticipated memories.
كذكريات متوقعة.
And basically you can look at this,
ويمكنك في الأساس النظر لهذا،
you know, as a tyranny of the remembering self,
كما تعلمون، بفعل طغيان نفسية الذكرى،
and you can think of the remembering self
يمكنك التفكير بنفسية الذكرى
sort of dragging the experiencing self
كنوع من إسقاط نفسية التجربة
through experiences that
على التجارب التي
the experiencing self doesn't need.
لا تحتاجها نفسية التجربة.
I have that sense that
لديّ ذلك الإحساس أنه
when we go on vacations
عندما نذهب للعطلات
this is very frequently the case;
فان هذا هو الوضع في أغلب الأحيان،
that is, we go on vacations,
وهو، أننا نذهب للعطلات،
to a very large extent,
إلى حد كبير للغاية،
in the service of our remembering self.
لخدمة نفسية الذكرى خاصتنا.
And this is a bit hard to justify I think.
وهذا من الصعب قليلاً تبريره كما أعتقد.
I mean, how much do we consume our memories?
أعني، إلى أي مدى نستهلك ذاكرتنا؟
That is one of the explanations
ذلك هو أحد التفسيرات
that is given for the dominance
التي تعطي كدليل على هيمنة
of the remembering self.
نفسية الذكرى.
And when I think about that, I think about a vacation
وعندما أفكر بذلك، أفكر حول العطلة
we had in Antarctica a few years ago,
التي قضيناها في القطب الجنوبي قبل سنوات قليلة مضت،
which was clearly the best vacation I've ever had,
التي كانت بكل وضوح أفضل عطلة أقضيها،
and I think of it relatively often,
وأفكر بها كثيراً ،
relative to how much I think of other vacations.
مقارنة بكثرة تفكيري ببقية العطلات.
And I probably have consumed
وعلى الأرجح أنني أستهلكت
my memories of that three-week trip, I would say,
ذكرياتي لرحلة الثلاث أسابيع تلك، أستطيع القول،
for about 25 minutes in the last four years.
لحوالي 25 دقيقة في السنوات الأربع الأخيرة.
Now, if I had ever opened the folder
الآن، إن كنت قد فتحت الملف
with the 600 pictures in it,
الذي يحوي 600 صورة،
I would have spent another hour.
لكنت قد قضيت ساعة أخرى.
Now, that is three weeks,
الآن، تلك ثلاثة أسابيع ،
and that is at most an hour and a half.
وتلك تقريباً ساعة ونصف .
There seems to be a discrepancy.
يبدو أن هناك تباين.
Now, I may be a bit extreme, you know,
الآن، ربما أكون ابالغ قليلاً، كما تعلمون،
in how little appetite I have for consuming memories,
في رغبتي القليلة عن تلك الذكريات الاستهلاكية التي املك
but even if you do more of this,
لكن حتى وإن فعلت المزيد من هذا - صنع الذكريات-،
there is a genuine question:
فان هناك سؤالاً حقيقياً.
Why do we put so much weight on memory
لماذا نضع الكثير من الأهمية للذكرى
relative to the weight that we put on experiences?
مقارنة بالأهمية التي نضعها على التجارب؟
So I want you to think
إذاً أريدكم أن تفكروا
about a thought experiment.
حول تجربة فكرية.
Imagine that for your next vacation,
تخيلوا أن عطلتكم القادمة
you know that at the end of the vacation
أنكم تعلمون أن في نهاية العطلة
all your pictures will be destroyed,
سيتم تخريب كل الصور خاصتكم،
and you'll get an amnesic drug
وأن ستتناولون دواء محو الذاكرة
so that you won't remember anything.
بحيث أنكم لن تتذكروا أي شئ.
Now, would you choose the same vacation? (Laughter)
الآن، هل ستقومون بإختيار نفس العطلة؟ (ضحك)
And if you would choose a different vacation,
وإن كنتم ستختارون عطلة مختلفة،
there is a conflict between your two selves,
فان هناك تناقض ما نفسييتيك،
and you need to think about how to adjudicate that conflict,
وستحتاج للتفكير حول كيفية فصل ذلك النزاع،
and it's actually not at all obvious, because
وانه في الواقع ليس واضحاً بتاتاً بسبب،
if you think in terms of time,
إن فكرت بالسياق الزمني،
then you get one answer,
فعندها ستحصلون على إجابة.
and if you think in terms of memories,
وإن فكرت بسياق الذكريات،
you might get another answer.
فربما تحصلون على إجابة أخرى.
Why do we pick the vacations we do
لم نختار العطلات التي نقضيها،
is a problem that confronts us
هي مشكلة تواجهنا
with a choice between the two selves.
مع الخيار بين النفسييتين.
Now, the two selves
الآن، النفسييتان
bring up two notions of happiness.
تبرز فكرتين حول السعادة.
There are really two concepts of happiness
إن هناك مفهومين للسعادة
that we can apply, one per self.
التي نقوم بتطبيقها، مفهوم لكل نفسية.
So you can ask: How happy is the experiencing self?
إذاً يمكنك طرح سؤال: كم هي سعيدة نفسية التجربة؟
And then you would ask: How happy are the moments
ثم تسأل: كم كانت اللحظات سعيدة
in the experiencing self's life?
في حياة نفسية التجربة؟
And they're all -- happiness for moments
وهم جميعاً -- السعادة للحظات
is a fairly complicated process.
عملية معقدة للغاية.
What are the emotions that can be measured?
ما هي المشاعر التي يمكن قياسها؟
And, by the way, now we are capable
وبالمناسبة، نحن قادرون
of getting a pretty good idea
على أخذ فكرة جيدة للغاية
of the happiness of the experiencing self over time.
لسعادة نفسية التجربة عبر الزمن.
If you ask for the happiness of the remembering self,
إذا سألت عن سعادة نفسية التجربة،
it's a completely different thing.
فانها مختلفة كلياً.
This is not about how happily a person lives.
هذا ليس حول شخص يعيش بسعادة.
It is about how satisfied or pleased the person is
إنها حول كم هو راض أو سعيد
when that person thinks about her life.
عندما يفكر الشخص بحياته.
Very different notion.
فكرة مختلفة كلياً.
Anyone who doesn't distinguish those notions
أي شخص لا يفرّق بين تلك المفاهيم،
is going to mess up the study of happiness,
سيقوم بالعبث بدراسة السعادة،
and I belong to a crowd of students of well-being,
وأنا أنتمي لمجموعة دارسي الرفاهية،
who've been messing up the study of happiness for a long time
الذين كانوا يعبثون بدراسة السعادة لوقت طويل
in precisely this way.
بهذه الطريقة على وجه التحديد.
The distinction between the
الفرق بين
happiness of the experiencing self
سعادة نفسية التجربة
and the satisfaction of the remembering self
والرضا لنفسية الذكرى
has been recognized in recent years,
تم التعرف عليها في السنوات الأخيرة،
and there are now efforts to measure the two separately.
وهناك جهود الآن لقياس الأثنين كلٌ على حدى،
The Gallup Organization has a world poll
لمركز غالوب إستطلاع عالمي
where more than half a million people
مع أكثر من نصف مليون شخص
have been asked questions
تم سؤالهم
about what they think of their life
حول ما هو إعتقادهم عن حياتهم
and about their experiences,
وعن تجاربهم.
and there have been other efforts along those lines.
وكانت هناك جهوداً أخرى بجانب هذه الجهود.
So in recent years, we have begun to learn
لذا ففي السنوات الأخيرة، بدأنا التعلم
about the happiness of the two selves.
حول السعادة للنفسييتين.
And the main lesson I think that we have learned
والدرس الرئيسي الذي أعتقد أننا تعلمناه،
is they are really different.
هو أنهما مختلفتان حقاً.
You can know how satisfied somebody is with their life,
يمكنك معرفة مدى رضى الشخص مع حياتهم،
and that really doesn't teach you much
وذلك بالطبع لا يعلمك كثيراً
about how happily they're living their life,
عن كم السعادة الذي يعيشوه في حياتهم،
and vice versa.
والعكس صحيح.
Just to give you a sense of the correlation,
لأعطيكم شعور بالترابط،
the correlation is about .5.
فان العلاقة هي حوالي فاصل خمسة.
What that means is if you met somebody,
ما يعنيه ذلك هو أنك إن إلتقيت بشخص ما،
and you were told, "Oh his father is six feet tall,"
وتم إخبارك، أوه يبلغ طول والده ستة أقدام،
how much would you know about his height?
كم ستعرف حول طوله؟
Well, you would know something about his height,
حسناً، ستعرف شيئاً حول طوله،
but there's a lot of uncertainty.
لكن هناك الكثير من عدم اليقين.
You have that much uncertainty.
لديك الكثير من عدم اليقين.
If I tell you that somebody ranked their life eight on a scale of ten,
إذا أخبرتك أن شخص ما يعطي حياته ثمانية من مجموع عشرة،
you have a lot of uncertainty
سيكون لديك الكثير من عدم اليقين
about how happy they are
حول كم هو سعيد
with their experiencing self.
مع نفسية تجاربهم.
So the correlation is low.
إذاً فالعلاقة منخفضة.
We know something about what controls
نحن نعرف شيئاً حول ما يقوم بالسيطرة
satisfaction of the happiness self.
على رضى نفسية السعادة.
We know that money is very important,
نحن نعرف أن المال مهم جداً،
goals are very important.
الأهداف مهمة جداً.
We know that happiness is mainly
نحن نعرف أن السعادة عامةً
being satisfied with people that we like,
يتم تحقيقها مع الناس الذين نحبهم،
spending time with people that we like.
بقضاء وقت مع من نحبهم.
There are other pleasures, but this is dominant.
هناك مُتع أخرى، لكن هذا هو المهيمن.
So if you want to maximize the happiness of the two selves,
إذاً إن كنت تريد زيادة سعادة النفسييتين،
you are going to end up
فأنك ستصل في نهاية المطاف
doing very different things.
لفعل أشياء مختلفة كلياً.
The bottom line of what I've said here
إن خلاصة ما قلته هنا
is that we really should not think of happiness
هو أننا لا ينبغي أن نفكر بالسعادة
as a substitute for well-being.
كبديل للرفاهية.
It is a completely different notion.
إنها مفاهيم مختلفة كلياً.
Now, very quickly,
الآن، بسرعة جداً،
another reason we cannot think straight about happiness
سبب آخر لعدم مقدرتنا بالتفكير مباشرة حول السعادة
is that we do not attend to the same things
هو أننا لا نستحضر نفس الأشياء
when we think about life, and we actually live.
حينما نفكر بالحياة، ونحن في الواقع نعيشها.
So, if you ask the simple question of how happy people are in California,
إذاً، إن سألت السؤال البسيط حول كم هم سعداء الناس الذين في كالفورنيا،
you are not going to get to the correct answer.
فانك لن تحصل على الإجابة الصحيحة.
When you ask that question,
عندما تسأل ذلك السؤال،
you think people must be happier in California
تعتقد أن الناس بالتأكيد أكثر سعادة في كالفورنيا،
if, say, you live in Ohio.
إن كنت تعيش، لنقل في أوهايو.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And what happens is
وما يحدث هو
when you think about living in California,
عندما تفكر بالحياة في كالفورنيا،
you are thinking of the contrast
فانك تفكر بالمقارنة
between California and other places,
بين كالفورنيا وأماكن أخرى،
and that contrast, say, is in climate.
وتلك المقارنة، لنقل، حول الطقس.
Well, it turns out that climate
حسناً، لقد وضح أن الطقس
is not very important to the experiencing self
مهم للغاية بالنسبة لنفسية التجربة
and it's not even very important to the reflective self
وهو ليس مهم بشدة لإنعكاس النفسية
that decides how happy people are.
التي تقرر كيفية سعادة الناس.
But now, because the reflective self is in charge,
لكن الآن، لأن إنعكاس النفسية ضالعة في الأمر،
you may end up -- some people may end up
فانك ستنتهي -- ربما ينتهي الحال ببعض الناس
moving to California.
بالإنتقال لكالفورنيا.
And it's sort of interesting to trace what is going to happen
والأمر نوعاً ما مثير لتتبع ما الذي يحدث
to people who move to California in the hope of getting happier.
عندما ينتقل الناس إلى كالفورنيا على أمل الحصول على سعادة اكثر.
Well, their experiencing self
حسناً، إن نفسية تجاربهم
is not going to get happier.
لن تصبح أكثر سعادة.
We know that.
نحن نعرف ذلك.
But one thing will happen: They will think they are happier,
لكن شئ ما سيحدث. أنهم سيعتقدون أنهم أكثر سعادة،
because, when they think about it,
لأنهم حينما يفكرون حول الأمر،
they'll be reminded of how horrible the weather was in Ohio,
فسيتذكرون كم كان الطقس فظيعاً في أوهايو.
and they will feel they made the right decision.
وسيشعرون أنهم قاموا باتخاذ القرار الصحيح.
It is very difficult
من الصعب جداً
to think straight about well-being,
التفكير مباشرة بالرفاهية،
and I hope I have given you a sense
وأأمل أن أكون قد أعطيتكم فكرة
of how difficult it is.
عن كم هي صعبة.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Chris Anderson: Thank you. I've got a question for you.
كريس أندرسون: شكراً لك. لدي سؤال لك.
Thank you so much.
شكراً جزيلاً لك.
Now, when we were on the phone a few weeks ago,
الآن، عندما كنا نتحدث على الهاتف قبل أسابيع قليلة،
you mentioned to me that there was quite an interesting result
ذكرت لي أن هناك نتائج مثيرة للغاية
came out of that Gallup survey.
جاءت من إستطلاع مركز غالوب.
Is that something you can share
هل هي شئ يمكنك تقاسمه
since you do have a few moments left now?
لأنه ما يزال لديك بعض الوقت المتبقي الآن؟
Daniel Kahneman: Sure.
دانيال كانيمان: بالطبع.
I think the most interesting result that we found in the Gallup survey
أعتقد أن أكثر النتائج إثارة التي وجدناها من إستطلاع غالوب
is a number, which we absolutely did not expect to find.
هو رقم، الذي بالطبع لن تتوقع أن تجده.
We found that with respect to the happiness
لقد وجدنا أنه بالنسبة لسعادة
of the experiencing self.
نفسية التجربة.
When we looked at how feelings,
عندما نظرنا لكيفية تباين
vary with income.
المشاعر مع الدخل الشخصي.
And it turns out that, below an income
وقد وضح أنه، تحت خط الدخل
of 60,000 dollars a year, for Americans --
ل 60،000 دولار سنوياً، للأمريكيين،
and that's a very large sample of Americans, like 600,000,
وتلك عينة كبيرة جداً للأمريكان، مثل 600،000،
so it's a large representative sample --
لكنها عينة تمثيلية كبيرة،
below an income of 600,000 dollars a year...
تحت خط الدخل 600،000 دولار سنوياً...
CA: 60,000.
كريس: 60،000.
DK: 60,000.
دانيال: 60،000.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
60,000 dollars a year, people are unhappy,
60،000 دولار سنوياً، الناس ليسوا سعداء،
and they get progressively unhappier the poorer they get.
ويصبحون أكثر تعاسة كلما كانوا أكثر فقراً.
Above that, we get an absolutely flat line.
فوق ذلك، نحن على خط مستوي بثبات.
I mean I've rarely seen lines so flat.
أعني انه من النادر جداً رؤية خطوط مستوية جداً.
Clearly, what is happening is
بكل وضوح، الذي يحدث هو
money does not buy you experiential happiness,
أن المال لا يجلب لك سعادة تجربة،
but lack of money certainly buys you misery,
لكن قلة المال بالتأكيد تجلب لك التعاسة،
and we can measure that misery
ويمكننا قياس تلك التعاسة
very, very clearly.
بكل وضوح.
In terms of the other self, the remembering self,
بالنسبة للنفسية الأخرى، نفسية الذكرى،
you get a different story.
تحصل على قصة مختلفة.
The more money you earn, the more satisfied you are.
كلما كسبت أموال أكثر كلما أصبحت أكثر رضى.
That does not hold for emotions.
هذا لا ينطبق على المشاعر.
CA: But Danny, the whole American endeavor is about
كريس: لكن داني، كل المساعي الأمريكية تدور حول
life, liberty, the pursuit of happiness.
الحياة، الحرية، السعي لتحقيق السعادة.
If people took seriously that finding,
إذا أخذ الناس تلك الحقائق بكل جدية،
I mean, it seems to turn upside down
أعني، يبدو أنها ستقلب كل شئ
everything we believe about, like for example,
رأساً على عقب حول إعتقادنا، لنقل كمثال،
taxation policy and so forth.
سياسة الضرائب وهلمجرا.
Is there any chance that politicians, that the country generally,
هل هناك أي فرصة أن يأخذ السياسيين في البلاد،
would take a finding like that seriously
هذه الحقائق بكل جدية
and run public policy based on it?
ويغيروا السياسات بناءً عليها؟
DK: You know I think that there is recognition
دانيال: كما تعلم أعتقد أن هناك إعتراف
of the role of happiness research in public policy.
بدور بحوث السعادة في السياسة العامة.
The recognition is going to be slow in the United States,
هذا الإعتراف سيكون منخفضاً في الولايات المتحدة،
no question about that,
لا شك حول ذلك،
but in the U.K., it is happening,
لكن في المملكة المتحدة، إنه يحدث،
and in other countries it is happening.
وفي بقية البلدان يحدث كذلك.
People are recognizing that they ought
يعترف الناس بأن عليهم
to be thinking of happiness
التفكير بالسعادة
when they think of public policy.
عندما يفكرون بالسياسة العامة.
It's going to take a while,
سيستغرق الأمر بعض الوقت،
and people are going to debate
وسيتجادل الناس
whether they want to study experience happiness,
سواء ارادوا دراسة تجربة السعادة،
or whether they want to study life evaluation,
أو سواء أرادوا دراسة تقييم الحياة،
so we need to have that debate fairly soon.
إذاً فنحن نحتاج لإقامة تلك المناظرات قريباً جداً،
How to enhance happiness
كيفية تحسين السعادة،
goes very different ways depending on how you think,
يذهب بطرق مختلفة كلياً إعتماداً على كيفية تفكيرك،
and whether you think of the remembering self
وسواء كنت تفكر بنفسية الذكرى
or you think of the experiencing self.
أم تفكر بنفسية التجربة.
This is going to influence policy, I think, in years to come.
سيقوم هذا بالتأثير على السياسة، كما أعتقد في سنوات لاحقة.
In the United States, efforts are being made
في الولايات المتحدة، تُبذل جهودا
to measure the experience happiness of the population.
لقياس تجربة السعادة للسكان.
This is going to be, I think, within the next decade or two,
سيكون هذا، كما أعتقد، خلال العقد أو العقدين القادمين
part of national statistics.
كجزء من الإحصاء الوطني.
CA: Well, it seems to me that this issue will -- or at least should be --
كريس، حسناً، يبدو بالنسبة لي، أن هذا الأمر سيكون، أو على الأقل ينبغي أن يكون
the most interesting policy discussion to track
أكثر النقاشات المثيرة في السياسة يمكن تتبعه
over the next few years.
خلال السنوات القليلة القادمة.
Thank you so much for inventing behavioral economics.
شكراً جزيلاً لك لإبتكارك علم الإقتصاد السلوكي.
Thank you, Danny Kahneman.
شكراً لك دانيي كانيمان.